Finding Aid for Robert Tisch Papers 1978-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Tisch Papers 1978-1997, 1980-1982
Tisch, Robert.
1 oversize folders
3 linear feet
Property tax reform advocate in the late 1970s and early 1980s from Laingsburg, Mich.; 1982 Michigan gubernatorial candidate, and founder of the Tisch Independent Citizens Party. Tisch was also active in the U.S. Taxpayers Party. Material pertaining primarily to Tisch's three campaigns to lower property taxes, as well as later political activities. Political files series consists of clippings, constituent correspondence, campaign business (official correspondence, minutes, ballot proposals, speeches), press releases, political cartoons, and copies of the Michigan Taxpayer, the newsletter of the U.S. Taxpayers Party of Michigan.
013 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from Bethel Tisch (donor 8961 ), widow of Robert Tisch, in May 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Robert Emanuel Tisch (known as Bob Tisch) was a tax-cut crusader mainly active in the 1970s and 1980s. He was known as much for his populist zeal and his direct, often abrasive, style, as he was for the three "Tisch Tax Cut" proposals he fought to have put on the ballot in the 1978, 1980, and 1982 Michigan elections.
Tisch was born March 28, 1920, in Jackson, Michigan. During World War II and the Korean War he served in the biological warfare unit of the Army. In the postwar years, Tisch settled in Laingsburg, a small community near Lansing. Over the years, he worked at a variety of pursuits, including sign-painting, milking machine sales, children's furniture manufacture, and cattle farming. He and his wife, Bethel, raised five children on their family farm.
Tisch was elected Shiawassee County Drain Commissioner in 1976 and continued to serve in this role until 1984, when he lost his bid for reelection. His previous political experience had included a turbulent and short-lived term on the Laingsburg school board in 1955 (he was recalled amidst bitter controversy) and time as a local judge.
The late seventies were a time of severe inflation and recession that hit Michigan particularly hard. Although an unlikely "professional" politician, Tisch, fed up with the situation and spurred on by the multitude of complaints he had been hearing from those around him, began a grassroots (and often self-funded) campaign to lower property taxes. He was denounced by many, both for the extremity of his plan and for his blunt, even profane, manner of speaking. Despite this opposition, however, Tisch and his plan achieved considerable popular support.
The 1978 Tisch tax cut proposal addressed a serious issue, sharply rising property taxes, but was considered by most to be extremely drastic in its way of dealing with the problem. Thus, many give credit to Tisch for scaring legislators into formulating and promoting the much more moderate Headlee Amendment, which eventually beat the Tisch plan. Ironically, however, Tisch considered the Headlee Amendment to be almost worse than nothing at all and continued to campaign relentlessly for versions of his proposal in the next two elections. The "Tisch II" plan, like its successor, was defeated at the polls. Tisch III, in 1982, did not receive enough petition signatures to make the ballot.
In addition to his tax cut campaigns, Tisch ran independently for governor in 1982. His bid for this office was unsuccessful, but his party, the Tisch Independent Citizens Party, garnered enough votes to automatically qualify for inclusion on the ballot in the next election. Tisch is the only Michigan person to date known to have had a major political party named for him. The Tisch Independent Citizens Party continued to qualify as a major political party through 1992.
In 1992 the Tisch Independent Citizens Party became affiliated with the conservative U.S. Taxpayers Party, and in 1993 it was officially renamed the U.S. Taxpayers Party of Michigan (also referred to sometimes as the "Michigan Taxpayers Party"). The Taxpayers Party favors eliminating income tax and most government programs. Tisch was active in the party on both the statewide and the national levels, serving as leader of the Michigan party, Chairman of the Central States, and Michigan Member of the National Committee. He even ran as presidential hopeful Howard Phillips' running mate for the U.S. Taxpayers Party in 1992. Ill health forced Tisch to resign from his party duties in 1996.
Tisch died October 9, 1997.
The Robert Tisch Papers consist primarily of material pertaining to Tisch's three campaigns to lower property taxes, his 1982 gubernatorial campaign, and his later political activities with the Tisch Independent Citizens Party (which later became the Michigan Taxpayers Party, a political affiliate of the U.S. Taxpayers Party). The Tisch Papers are made up of two series: Political files and Memorabilia. The collection is composed primarily of press coverage of the Tisch campaigns in the form of newspaper clippings, kept by a clippings service and by Tisch himself. Within files, material is arranged chronologically. Items for which a date could not be ascertained are in the back section of each folder or are in separate folders labeled "undated."
Subjects:
Tisch, Robert.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; Elections--Michigan--1980.; Elections--Michigan--1982.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.; Property tax--Michigan.; Tisch Independent Citizens Party.; U.S. Taxpayers Party of Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Tisch, Robert.; Political elections--Michigan--1982.; Shiawassee County (Mich.). Drain Commission.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Political cartoons.
- Political files 1972-1997, 2.9 linear feet
  The Political files series (2.9 linear feet) consists of two chronological subseries, "1978-1982" and "1983-1997."
  - 1978-1982
    The 1978-1982 subseries is divided into three sub-subseries (Clippings, Constituent correspondence, and Campaign business). This subseries contains materials relating to Tisch's tax cut campaigns in 1978, 1980, and 1982 and his 1982 campaign for governor. The fullest documentation relates to the 1980 tax cut campaign ("Tisch II").
    - Clippings
      The Clippings sub-subseries is comprised of clippings from the Michigan Press Reading service. These clippings, spanning the months of July to November of 1980, provide a detailed account of the Tisch II campaign process. They are supplemented by the "Personal Clippings" that Tisch collected himself or had sent to him by friends and constituents. The Personal Clippings file also contains clippings on the earlier and later campaigns, some with handwritten notes or underscoring by Tisch on important points he wished to highlight. Some material in this file is undated and unsourced, but is kept because of its informative or colorful content. Also included in the file is a photograph showing Tisch in front of the Capitol building in Lansing. This photographs accompanies an article entitled "Tisch's Tax Cut Plan Keeps Politicians on Defense," from the London Free Press, dated December 29, 1981.
      - Michigan Press Reading Service July-November 1980
        - July 8, 1980-September 5, 1980 (Box 1)
        - September 5-17, 1980 (Box 1)
        - September 18-26, 1980 (Box 1)
        - September 27-30, 1980 (Box 1)
        - October 1-2, 1980 (Box 1)
        - October 3-6, 1980 (Box 1)
        - October 7-8, 1980 (Box 1)
        - October 9-11, 1980 (Box 1)
        - October 12-14, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 15, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 16-19, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 20-22, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 23-26, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 27-28, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 29, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 30, 1980 (Box 2)
        - October 31, 1980 (Box 2)
        - November 1-21, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Personal clippings
        - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        - February-September 1980 (Box 3)
          (includes extensive biographical article from the Lansing State Journal, September 14, 1980)
        - October-December 1980 (Box 3)
        - 1981 (Box 3)
        - 1981Photograph: Robert Tisch in front of State Capitol Building (Box 3)
          (accompanies the article entitled "Tisch's Tax Cut Plan Keeps Politicians on Defense," from the London Free Press December 29, 1981, page A10)
        - 1982 (Box 3)
        - Undated, circa 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - Constituent correspondence
      The Constituent correspondence sub-subseries consists mainly of letters of support from constituents. There are also some letters from schoolchildren requesting political and biographical information for school projects, which Tisch supplies. The files consist mainly of incoming correspondence.
      - 1980 (Box 3)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
        (includes autobiographical sketch)
      - circa 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - Campaign business
      The Campaign business sub-subseries is a grouping of items pertaining to Tisch's tax cut campaigns. Within this sub-subseries, the Administrative papers files contain the bulk of the material, including official correspondence, meeting minutes, ballot proposals, and speeches. In addition, although most of the political posters and flyers are located in the Memorabilia series, some were originally interspersed among the rest of the campaign business and so are left there. Also included in the Administrative papers file is one folder with a small number of items from 1976.
      The Press releases file contains press releases put out by a public relations firm on the Tisch campaigns spanning from 1980 to 1981. The Lawsuits file is comprised of materials relating to two lawsuits in which Tisch was involved. In the first one, dating from September 1980, Tisch was one of the defendants in a suit filed by Michigan State University law professor and political activist Zolton Ferency. The suit challenged the validity of the petitions that had been circulated for the Tisch II tax cut proposal and furthermore contested the constitutionality of Tisch II according to the Michigan state constitution. The second lawsuit, which Tisch filed against Governor Milliken and others, dates from October of 1980 and concerns the illegal use of state funds to attack the Tisch proposal.
      The Political cartoons file is an assembling of editorial cartoons, most of them from the Detroit News, relating to Tisch or his proposals. Most but not all of these cartoons can also be found dispersed among the Clippings files, sometimes along with the editorial article that originally accompanied the cartoon. Also included in the file is the signed original of a cartoon by News staff cartoonist Draper Hill.
      - Administrative papers: official correspondence, minutes, ballot proposals, speeches 1976, 1978-1982, 7 folders
        (includes some material from 1976)
        - 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        - February-August 1980 (Box 3)
        - September-December 1980 (Box 3)
        - circa 1980 (Box 3)
        - 1981 (Box 3)
        - 1982 (Box 3)
        - circa 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      - Press Releases 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - Speech drafts undated (Box 3)
        (handwritten speech drafts and notes)
      - Lawsuits: includes correspondence, official complaint documents, and transcripts, and some clippings 1980-1981 (Box 3)
        (1. Zolton Ferency vs. Richard Austin, George Herstek, Department of State, Board of State Canvassers, Tisch Coalition for Property Tax Cut in Michigan, Inc., 2. Robert Tisch et al. vs. Governor Milliken et al.)
      - Political cartoons
        - Newspaper copies 1980-1982 (Box 3)
          (many of these are also dispersed throughout the Clippings files)
        - Signed and framed original by Detroit News cartoonist Draper Hill, May 24, 1981 (Folder UAm)
  - 1983-1997
    The second subseries of the Political files series is "1983-1997." It contains material from what could be considered the latter part of Tisch's political career, in which he stopped his active campaigning for specific tax cut proposals and worked on the organization and promotion of his own independent political party, Tisch Independent Citizens for Michigan (later the U.S. Taxpayers Party of Michigan). The 1983-1997 subseries parallels the earlier subseries in its basic arrangement, with division into Clippings and Campaign business sub-subseries. Additionally, this subseries contains an Obituaries and eulogies file for Robert Tisch.
    The Drain Commission file within the Clippings sub-subseries contains articles relating to Tisch's work with the commission; in particular, these articles relate to youth corps work in Shiawassee County. This file also contains a photograph of Tisch and other Drain Commission staff, including his daughter.
    In the Campaign business sub-subseries will be found the Michigan Taxpayer, the newsletter of the U.S. Taxpayers Party of Michigan. It was begun by Robert Tisch and Joe Sanger, a longtime Tisch supporter and aide. Sanger continued to publish the newsletter after Tisch's death, with issues running through November 1998, that being the final regular issue. (In fact, Tisch's actual role in the publication of the newsletter, beyond that of "founder," is somewhat unclear.) In the October 1997 issue, Sanger wrote a eulogy to Tisch which is included here and in the Obituaries and eulogies subseries.
    - Clippings
      - 1983-1997 (Box 3)
      - Drain Commission 1984, undated
        - Clippings 1984, undated (Box 3)
        - Photograph: Tisch and Drain Commission staff, including Tisch's daughter on right 1981 (Folder UAm)
    - Campaign business
      - Administrative papers 1983-1997
        (chiefly correspondence)
        - 1983-1989 (Box 3)
        - 1990-1992 (Box 3)
        - 1993-1997 (Box 3)
        - circa 1990s (Box 3)
      - Biographical papers (Box 3)
        (includes resumes, clippings)
      - Michigan Taxpayer Newsletter, 1995-1998 (Box 3)
    - Obituaries and eulogies
      - Miscellaneous 1997 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  The Memorabilia series (0.1 linear feet) consists of political memorabilia mainly from the period 1978 to 1982 but also has items from 1983 to 1997. Among the items are campaign signs and flyers, stickers, buttons (removed to the library's campaign button collection), and a license plate. Also included are sample ballots. Photocopies of two memorial plaques to Tisch from December 1997 are among the later items. The original plaques are retained by Tisch's widow, Bethel Tisch. In addition, this series contains political ads or drafts of ads that Tisch and his supporters composed for the 1980 campaign.
  - 1978-1982 (Box 3)
  - 1983-1997 (Box 3)
    (includes award from U.S. Taxpayers Party)
  - Political ads 1980 (Box 3)
    (includes drafts of ads that Tisch composed from newspaper clippings he had compiled and edited, and some opposition ads)